Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse papers SSC.MS.00202
Sophia Smith Collection
Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse papers
1915-1999, 2008
Sophia Smith Collection
Barnhouse, Ruth Tiffany, 1923-1999
SSC.MS.00202
34.25 linear feet (35 boxes)
Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse was a psychiatrist, theologian, and ordained Episcopal priest known for being poet Syvia Plath's psychiatrist, and for her theological publications related to homosexuality, sex, and women in the Christian church. This collection contains materials reflecting both her personal and professional lives, most of it from about 1970 and later. The collection contains a small amount of materials related to Sylvia Plath, which have been put in separate series for ease of access and reference.
Conditions Governing Access
Series 1, 2, and 4 of this collection are open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Effective September 6, 2018, Series 3 of this collection is also open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Series 5, which currently contains the bulk of this collection, must be thoroughly reviewed by an archivist for confidential patient, ministerial, and student information prior to access. This series is being processed on demand; please contact Smith College Special Collections to request that a portion be processed for your use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse began donating her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1999. This collection is comprised of the following accessions received from Barnhouse, her estate, her family, and Harriet Rosenstein in 1999-2008 and 2018: 99S-14, 00S-35, 01S-21, 2017S-006, 2018-S-0024.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in five series: the first contains a small trove of letters from Barnhouse's parents that she kept in a special box throughout her life and which were sent to the archives in 2008; the second contains all known Sylvia Plath-related files in the collection, which have been separated for ease of access and reference; the third contains 14 letters from Sylvia Plath to Ruth Beuscher (later Ruth Barnhouse) obtained from Harriet Rosenstein; the fourt contains materials from Barnhouse's papers that have been thoroughly screened for confidential information and are open for use; the fifth contains all unprocessed materials which must be reviewed for confidential patient and pastoral information prior to access. Materials within the fifth series are arranged into subseries by the accession with which they were received.
Biographical Note
Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse was a Jungian psychiatrist, theologian, and ordained Episcopal priest known for being poet Sylvia Plath's psychiatrist, and for her theological publications and teachings related to homosexuality, sex, and women in the Christian church.
Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse was born in France in 1923. She was schooled in France and Germany before World War II. She received her B.A. from Barnard College, M.D. from Columbia University, and Th.M. from the Weston College School of Theology (Jesuit). She began private practice as a psychiatrist in 1956. As an attending staff psychiatrist at McLean Hospital, she served as psychiatrist to poet Sylvia Plath. She was also a clinical assistant in psychology at Harvard University.
Barnhouse moved to Washington, D.C. in 1978 and worked as adjunct professor of pastoral theology at the Virginia Theological Seminary. From 1980-1989, she was on the faculty of Dallas's Southern Methodist University as professor of psychiatry and pastoral care at the Perkins School of Theology. Also in 1980, she was ordained a priest in the Episcopal Church.
In 1991, she began working as a consultant to the human resources department of a major Dallas corporation. She was a co-founder of the Dallas chapter of the Physicians for Social Responsibility. She was the president of Peacemakers, Inc., which put on an international women's conference entitled "Global Peace...from Vision to Reality" in 1988. She was also president of the Isthmus Institute, an organization concerned with the interactions between scientific and religious approaches to reality. She was an assistant editor of the Anglican Theological Review and a past president of the Conference of Anglican Theologians. She served on the joint commission on health and human affairs of the general convention of the Episcopal Church. She was the first woman and first lay person to be a fellow of the College of Preachers in Washington, D.C. and she served on its council as chair of the program and policy committee for six years.
She frequently gave lectures, workshops, and radio-tv interviews acorss the country for psychiatric professional societies, mental health centers, pastors'schools, clergy and lay retreats, and civic groups. She is author of numerous publications including Homosexuality: A symbolic confusion (1977), Identity(1987), Clergy and the Sexual Revolution(1987), Sex and War (1991), A Woman's Identity (1994), and co-editor of Female: Christian Approaches to Sexuality.
Related Materials
The papers of Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse's father, fundamentalist Presbyterian minister Donald Grey Barnhouse are located in the archives of the Presbyterian Historical Society (RG 480).
Researchers interested in Sylvia Plath should also review the Sylvia Plath collection at Smith College Special Collections (MRBC.MS.00045).
Scope and Contents
The papers of this clergywoman and psychotherapist reflect both her personal and professional life. Viewed as conservative in Boston/Cambridge and wildly radical in Dallas, these papers provide valuable insight into the spiritual journey of a woman within the structure of the Christian church. Contains personal and professional papers from 1915-96 related to her work as an Episcopal priest and psychotherapist, including correspondence, printed material, video and audio cassette tapes, photographs, memorabilia, manuscripts, writings, and speeches.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Episcopal church--History--Sources; Ordination of women--Episcopal Church; Sex--Religious aspects--Christianity; Spirituality--Christianity; Women clergy--United States--Biography--Sources; Gender identity; Homosexuality--Religious aspects--Christianity; Sermons; Plath, Sylvia; correspondence; Manuscripts; Audiotapes; Videotapes; photographs; memorabilia; Interviews
- Correspondence from Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse's family and friends during her teen years, 1938-1941, 2008; 1; Barnhouse, Dorothy G; 0.25 linear feet (1 half document box) (Box 1)
  Custodial History
  According to correspondence from Dorothy G. Barnhouse, she acquired the materials in January 2008 from Ruth's son, Chris Beuscher, who had received them from his brother, Will Beuscher, who had, in turn, retrieved them from the basement of their brother Bob's house where Ruth Barnhouse lived for a short time before her death.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence, much of it from her parents, and a small amount of other material from Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse's teen years, which she saved in a box for her entire life. The series also contains one folder of printoffs of family history, rememberances about Ruth, and context for these materials written by her sister, Dorothy G. Barnhouse.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  The materials in this series were received from Ruth Barnhouse's sister, Dorothy G. Barnhouse, in 2008. They are accession 2017-S-0006.
  Arrangement
  The materials in this series have not been arranged in any particular order, however, it is unknown if they have remained in the order in which they were received in the archives.
  Barnhouse, Dorothy G
- Files and clippings regarding Sylvia Plath, 1971-1992, 1998; 2; 0.25 linear feet (1 half document box) (Box 2)
  This series consists of four folders of materials, mostly correspondence, kept by Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse about Sylvia Plath. The files document attempts, successful and unsuccessful, by numerous Plath biographers to interview Barnhouse about her famous former patient. The correspondence documents a shift in her attitude from the early 1970s, when she "steadfastly refused to talk to anyone by Harriet" (Rosenstein), to 1990 when she wrote to Rosenstein that she received many inquiries but "my memory has faded considerably" and she asked for Rosenstein to return Plath's letters to her so that she could be "as factual as possible" when speaking of Plath.
  Also included are a small number of clippings Barnhouse collected about Plath from 1998, when Ted Hughes' book Birthay Letters was published.
  These are the entirety of the known materials about Plath in boxes of Barnhouse's records sent to Smith College in 1999 and 2000. They have been screened and temporarily separated out from the rest of the accessions for ease of reference and access.
  The files about Plath remain organized as Barnhouse sent them to Smith College; the loose clippings have been put in a single folder.
- Sylvia Plath letters to Ruth Beuscher (later Ruth Barnhouse), 1960-1963; 3; 0.25 linear feet (14 items in one half-width letter size document box)
  These letters were received in 2018 from Harriet Rosenstein, who had obtained them from Barnhouse during the course of her research into Sylvia Plath.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  These letters have been digitized, and the digital copies can be provided to remote researchers upon request.
  The letters have been published in the second volume of The Letters of Sylvia Plath (2018).
  This series consists of 14 letters written by Sylvia Plath to her former therapist, Ruth Beuscher (later known as Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse), while living in London. The letters date from February 1960 to February 1963, and are of a highly personal nature. In them, Plath discusses her life, including difficulties in her marriage to poet Ted Hughes, and seeks Beuscher/Barnhouse's advice.
  Biographical / Historical
  Dr. Ruth Beuscher (as Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse was then known) and Sylvia Plath met in 1953, when Beuscher treated Plath during her hospitalization at McLean Hospital following Plath's first suicide attempt. Plath continued private therapy with Dr. Beuscher in person through 1959, and continued a relationship that, by Barnhouse's later accounts, crossed lines between friendship and therapy by letter until Plath's death from suicide in 1963. Although Barnhouse destroyed Plath's earlier letters to her, she retained these from the last few years of Plath's life.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Effective September 6, 2018, these letters are open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
  Related Materials
  A few of Ruth Barnhouse's letters to Sylvia Plath may be found in the Sylvia Plath papers in the Mortimer Rare Book Collection.
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1960 February 18; 2 pages (Two typewritten pages on one sheet of paper) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1960 April 2; 2 pages (Two typewritten pages on one sheet of paper) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1960 November 07; 4 pages (4 typewritten pages on 2 sheets of paper) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1961 January 4; 7 pages (7 typewritten pages on 4 sheets of paper) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Letter mis-dated as January 4, 1960 by author
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 March 27; 2 pages (Two typewritten pages on one sheet of paper) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 July 11; 6 pages (6 typewritten pages on 3 sheets of paper) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 July 20; 3 pages (Three typewritten pages on three sheets of paper) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 July 30; 4 pages (Four typewritten pages on four sheets of paper) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 September 4; 2 pages (Two typewritten pages on one sheet of paper) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 September 22; 4 pages (Four typewritten pages on four sheets of paper) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 September 29; 2 pages (Two typewritten pages on one sheet of paper) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 October 9; 2 pages (Two typewritten pages on one sheet of paper) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1962 October 21; 3 pages (Three typewritten pages on three sheets of paper) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sylvia Plath letter to Ruth Beuscher, 1963 February 4; 2 pages (Two typewritten pages on one sheet of paper) (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse personal and professional papers, 1951-1996; 1976-1996; 4; 8.437 linear feet (10 containers)
  The contents of this series were received in the first accession of materials given to the Sophia Smith Collection by Ruth Barnhouse (accession 1999-S-0014), which was received shortly before her death in 1999.
  This series consists of materials from accession 1999-S-0040 that have been screened for confidential patient and pastoral information, and so are open to research. The remainder of the accession, which has not yet been reviewed by an archivist, is described in Series 5, Subseries 1.
  This materials in this series were acquired directly from Ruth Barnhouse shortly before her death, and comprise a record of her careers as a Jungian psychotherapist, Episcopal priest, professor of theology, writer, and public speaker, as well as her personal and professional relationships.
  This series includes some biographical information, materials related to an unpublished book on Christian ethics, and approximately half of her alphabetical correspondence files (A through Me). For most of her professional life, Barnhouse employed an administrative assistant who typed much of her correspondence and maintained these correspondence files. Barnhouse's correspondences, and the files, make very few distinctions between people for whom she served as a psychoanalyst, personal friends, and professional colleagues. It was not uncommon for someone to begin their relationship with Barnhouse in one of these categories and traverse all of them over the course of a years-long relationship. Many of her correspondents were members of the Episcopal or Catholic churches with whom she discussed topics ranging from the politics of professional organizations, to her personal and professional lives, to questions of spirituality, religion, and the occult. Of particular interest to researchers may be her discussion and defense of the ideas in her 1978 book Homosexuality: A Symbolic Confusion with sympathetic friends and like-minded colleagues, as well as her discussions of her career and struggles as one of the first women to be ordained as a priest in the Episcopal church.
  This series also contains 185 audio recordings, many of them consisting of multiple audiocassette tapes. Most of the recordings appear to be of talks, lectures, and sermons that Barnhouse gave in a variety of settings, although a few of them are recordings of astrological readings Barnhouse had done for herself or others.
  The audio recordings were organized and cataloged, and many of them transcribed, by Barnhouse's assistants. However, all that remains today of that work is the tapes themselves and the numbering system, which employs a two-letter abbreviation: SP, PR, OP, MF, S, FP, J, P, or PW. The key to that encoding, as well as most of the transcripts, were lost before they reached the archives. A few transcripts remain in the unprocessed portions of the accession.
  The files in this series remain arranged in the order in which they were received in the archives.
  - Biographical material, 1980-1999 (Box 4)
    Includes a file of clippings about Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse, a biographical sketch, CV's, and medical licensures
  - Research files, outlines, drafts, and editorial comments on a never-published book on Christian ethics by Ruth Barnhouse and Philip Turner, around 1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence to Bishop Craig B. Anderson and Albert Aschaffenburg, 1984, 1995 (Box 4)
    Filed by Barnhouse under "Misc. "A" Correspondence"
  - Correspondence with Harry and Penny Abernathy, and text of Barnhouse's talk at Harry Abernathy's ordination, 1986-1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Nancy Ackley, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with and about Cary Baynes, 1975-1978 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Sam Bass, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Christmas letter from Ernie Bel, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Lee Collum of "D" Magazine, 1983-1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with and on behalf of Nadine Bell, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Anstis Benfield, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence to Treasury Secretary Bentsen, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence to Peter Berry, 1990-1996 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Adam Blatner, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Victor Bloom, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Kerry Bluglass, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with and about Jorge Bolet, 1951-1989; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Neville Boundy, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Jim Bowler, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence to David Briggs, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Alice Brennan, 1991-1996 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Edmond L. Browning and Robert Boznak, 1980, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence to John and Gladys Burke, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Harry Bumpus, 1974-1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Blayney Colmore and Ralph Cousins, 1989, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with J. M. Cameron regarding Barnhouse's book on homosexuality, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Judy Campbell, approximately 1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with John Caputo, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Helen Caradon-Sharp, 1992-1994 (Box 4)
  - Letter to Richard Carlson, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Margaret Carlyle, 1985-1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with James and Elizabeth Carlyle, approximately 1985 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Sumter M. Carmichael, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Letter to Peter F. Carnley, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from John Paul Carter, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Vivian Castleberry, 1986-1988 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Sue Chance, 1988-1996; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with John B. Coburn, 1976-1987 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with William and Lucille Clarkson, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Robert Coles, 1975-1977, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Robert Marsh Cooper, 1975-1994 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Michael Kraurz and Connie Costigan, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Tom Culley, 1972, 1974, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Philip Duncan, Carolyn Dunn, and others, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Bob de San Marzano, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from and on behalf of Mimi Davis, 1989-1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Larry Daywitt, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Vine Deloria, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with James K. Devlin, 1991-1993 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Joseph Devlin, 1972-1995 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Hugh Dickinson, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with John W. Dixon, 1975-1990; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes a letter from Barnhouse dated January 31, 1976 in wich she discusses Sylvia Plath and The Bell Jar in response to Dixon having read and commented on it in his previous letter.
  - Correspondence with Robert G. Doherty, 1980, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with William Dols, Jr., 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Larry Dossey, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with and about Kate Duncan, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Bruce and Margaret Duncan, 1991-1996 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Walton Ehrhardt, Janelle Ellis, and "Javier", 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence from Sir John Eccles, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with "Elizabeth", 1989, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with and about Mischa Epper-Quarles, 1973-1978 (Box 5)
  - Christmas letter from Julie and Terrry Fulkerson, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with "Kitty Farmer, Agent", 1994-1996 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with John Fesperman, 1989-1996 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Joseph Fichter, 1986-1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Laura Fisher, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Paul Fleischman, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Joseph Fletcher, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with James Fowler, 1982, 1993; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Jerome Frank, 1982, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Letter from John H. Freer, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Dorris H. Gray, Sanford Garner, Phil Graham, Jose Gonzalez, and Tom Grum, 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence from Brenda Garcia, around 1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence from Ken Gjemre, Halfprice Books, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Raelene Gold, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Louise Goldwater, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Letter to William Golightly, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Dick Goldwater and Ruth Balser, 1978-1983 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Roberto L. Gomez, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Letter from Henry Gray to all SMU faculty and staff, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with and about Paulos Mar Gregorios, 1991-1995 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence from Gwynette Grier, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Phone message from Rosemary Griggs, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Cassandra Guest, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Barbara Halpern, Emily Haines, Susan Hendrikson, Kay Bailey Hutchison, and other "Miscellaneous "H""s, 1991-1995 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Ben Habito, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with James Hall, 1979-1984 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence from Nancy Halsey, 1992, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence from Ronny and Jane Hardaway, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Letter to Anne Harrison, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Announcement of joining a law firm for Wyatt H. Heard, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Letter to Martha Gustuson Hendricks, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with James Hillman, 1973-1975 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Lorin Hollander and Nan Smith, 1990 (Box 5)
  - File containing a single sheet titled "Clarification of some of the terms used by Urban holmes in the Introduction to A History of Christian Spirituality, around 1990 (Box 5)
  - Letter to Susan Horton, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Mila Hradecna, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Ernest Hunt, 1991-1994 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with ICCB/North America, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Letter to Eva Ihlar, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence from Kermit and Lynn Johnson, and letter to "Justin", 1989, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Alan Jones, 1991, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Letter from Louise Jones, around 1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Richard S. Jones, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Postcard for Michael Krausz exhibition, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Chatsumarn Kabilsingh, 1986, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Ruth Gannett (Kahn), 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Edmund F. Kal, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Steven Kalas, 1988-1996 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Linda Kelly, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Lorna Khoo, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Stephen Kille of The Unification Church, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Hae Ahm Kim, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Michael Krausz, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Letter to Charles E. Kiblinger, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Ursula King, Robert Kress, Michael Krausz and other "K" correspondents, 1987-1995 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Hilde Korseck, 1972 (Box 5)